Guide to the Linda Mary Montano Papers MSS.386
Fales Library and Special Collections
Linda Mary Montano Papers
1931-2021
Fales Library and Special Collections
Montano, Linda, 1942-
MSS.386
130.25 Linear Feet in 162 containers, 1 folder in shared housing, and 2 oversize folders in shared housing
8.20 Terabytes
2 websites in 2 archived websites.
Linda Montano is a ground-breaking feminist performance artist whose work uses artistic ritual to focus on spiritual energy states and the removal of boundaries between art and life. Her early performances include "Handcuff" (1973) and "Three Day Blindfold" (1974). In 1983 and 1984, Montano participated in Tehching Hsieh's "Art / Life: One Year Performance (Rope Piece)," in which the two artists were bound to each other by a short length of rope 24 hours a day for a year. Montano's next work was "Seven Years of Living Art" (1984-1991), an endurance performance based on the Chakras -- work which has continued to the present. The Linda Montano Papers comprise performance proposals, professional and personal correspondence, drafts of published and unpublished works, creative writing, interviews, press and promotional materials, research files, personal and performance photographic material, artworks, work documenting collaborations with other artists, teaching materials, juvenilia and family-inspired work, costumes, selections from Montano's personal library, and both commercially released and non-commercially released media. The collection also includes an archived capture of the artist's website, which features her work and information about her. These materials document Montano's life as an author, teacher, and work as a performance artist for almost fifty years.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The collection was donated to NYU Libraries in 2013; the accession number associated with the original donation is 2013.386. An accretion to the collection was donated in 2015; the accession number associated with this accretion is 2017.092. An accretion to the collection was donated in June 2021; the accession number associated with this accretion is 2021.015. An accretion to the collection was donated in October 2022; the accession number associated with this accretion is 2023.031. Montano donated a further accretion in December 2023; the accession number associated with this accretion is 2024.010.
http://www.lindamontano.com/ and http://lindamarymontano.blogspot.com/ were selected by curators and captured through the use of Archive-It. Archive-It uses web crawling technology to capture websites at a scheduled time and displays only an archived copy, from the resulting WARC file, of the website. Th accession number associated with these websites are 2017.018.
Take Down Policy
Archived websites are made accessible for purposes of education and research. NYU Libraries have given attribution to rights holders when possible; however, due to the nature of archival collections, we are not always able to identify this information.
If you hold the rights to materials in our archived websites that are unattributed, please let us know so that we may maintain accurate information about these materials.
If you are a rights holder and are concerned that you have found material on this website for which you have not granted permission (or is not covered by a copyright exception under US copyright laws), you may request the removal of the material from our site by submitting a notice, with the elements described below, to the special.collections@nyu.edu.
Please include the following in your notice: Identification of the material that you believe to be infringing and information sufficient to permit us to locate the material; your contact information, such as an address, telephone number, and email address; a statement that you are the owner, or authorized to act on behalf of the owner, of an exclusive right that is allegedly infringed and that you have a good-faith belief that use of the material in the manner complained of is not authorized by the copyright owner, its agent, or the law; a statement that the information in the notification is accurate and made under penalty of perjury; and your physical or electronic signature. Upon receiving a notice that includes the details listed above, we will remove the allegedly infringing material from public view while we assess the issues identified in your notice.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged and described at the file level, and its arrangement is based on the artist's original order. Original folder titles were maintained where possible; files without original titles were named accordingly. More information on the artist's original divisions can be found in the Scope and Content notes at the series level.
Oversize materials, objects, and media were removed from their original locations to allow for adequate housing and preservation and can be found towards the end of the finding aid.
The Linda Montano Papers are arranged into 10 series:
Series I: Art Practice
Series II: Inspirational People and Collaborators
Series III: Correspondence
Series IV: Teaching
Series V: Family and Juvenilia
Series VI: Commerically Released Media
Series VII: Non-commercially Released Media
Series VIII: Data Storage
Series IX: Objects
Series X: Library
Series XI: Restricted Files
Series XII: 2021 Accretion
Series XIII: Archived Websites
Biographical Note
Linda Montano was born in 1942 in Saugerties, New York. Raised as a devout Roman Catholic, Montano's childhood was infused with a blended influence of Catholic ritual and artistic endeavor. After studying at the College of New Rochelle for a year, Montano joined the novitiate of the Maryknoll Sisters. She left the convent two years later, suffering from anorexia, and pursued an arts degree from the College of New Rochelle, graduating in 1965. Both the convent and the disorder would later become part of her performance life.
During the '60s and early '70s, Montano developed an interest in performance art and graduated with an MFA from the University of Wisconsin-Madison in 1969. Her thesis project, "The Chicken Show," was later adapted and became her first performance art piece, "The Chicken Woman." Through the '70s, Montano's performances covered a variety of subjects, ranging from the influence of the Catholic Church on her life, to testing the boundaries of her physicality, and to the role healing practices can play in art. Montano's early performances include "Handcuff" (1973), in which she was handcuffed to artist Tom Marioni for three days, and "Three Day Blindfold" (1974). In 1983 and 1984, Montano participated in Tehching Hsieh's "One Year Performance," in which the two artists were bound to each other by a short length of rope 24 hours a day for one year.
In 1984, Montano began the performance "Seven Years of Living Art", in which she lived out the energy qualities of a specific chakra for seven years. Montano has also performed "Art/Life Counseling," at the New Museum and other venues, using palm, tarot, and psychic readings in order to respond to her subjects' problems in creative ways. Montano often appears and performs as Saint Teresa of Avila; Mother Teresa of Calcutta; Bob Dylan; Hillary Clinton, and Woodstock musician Paul McMahon.
Montano has taught performance art at numerous institutions, most notably at the University of Texas at Austin. Her time there resulted in her book, Letters from Linda Montano, edited by Jennie Klein. In addition to teaching, Montano has written several other books, including You Too Are a Performance Artist, ART IN EVERYDAY LIFE, and a book of interviews entitled Performance Artists Talking in the Eighties.
Source, http://www.lindamontano.com/artist-bio/
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Access to some audiovisual materials in this collection is available through digitized access copies. Researchers may view an item's original container, but the media themselves are not available for playback because of preservation concerns. Materials that have already been digitized are noted in the collection's finding aid and can be requested in our reading room.
Audiovisual materials that have not been preserved may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. Materials that have already been digitized are noted in the collection's finding aid and can be requested in our reading room. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact Fales Library, special.collections@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596 with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Born-Digital Access Policies and Procedures
Born-digital materials have not been transferred and may not be available to researchers. Researchers may request access copies. To request that material be transferred, or if you are unsure if material has been transferred, please contact Fales Library, special.collections@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596 with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Related Materials
A.I.R. Gallery Archives, MSS 184
Artists Space Archive, MSS 291
Exit Art Archive, MSS 343
Franklin Furnace Ephemera Collection, MSS 206
Group Material Archive, MSS 215
Public Art Fund Archive, MSS 270
Scope and Contents
This collection includes performance proposals, professional and personal correspondence, drafts of published and unpublished works, creative writing, interviews, press and promotional materials, research files, personal and performance photographic material, artworks, work documenting collaborations with other artists, teaching materials, juvenilia and family-inspired work, costumes, selections from Montano's personal library, and both commercially released and non-commercially released media. The collection also includes an archived capture of the artist's website, which features her work and information about her. These materials document Montano's life as an author and teacher, and her work as a performance artist for almost fifty years.
Series I:
Series II:
Series III: Correspondence includes letters and postcards sent and received from students, fans, and other artists. The correspondence in this series is primarily of a personal nature. Business correspondence can be found in Series I, Subseries A.
Series IV: Teaching includes syllabi, course evaluations, term papers, and theses primarily documenting Montano's professorship at University of Texas at Austin. It also includes performance art and writing related to the tenure process at UT: Austin.
Series V: Family and Juvenilia contains diaries, certificates, scrapbooks, and materials related to family members and Montano's time spent at a convent between 1960 and 1962.
Series VI: Commercially Released Media contains both audio and video materials.
Series VII: Non-commercially Released Media contains audio, video, and film materials primarily related to Montano's performances.
Series VIII: Data Storage contains DVD-R, CD-R, and floppy discs, primarily related to work on Montano's books. Related paper material can be found in Series I, Subseries B.
Series IX: Objects contains artworks, woodcuts, and costumes.
Series X: Library contains books, periodicals, exhibition catalogues, and other print material owned by Montano.
Audiocassettes.; Photographs.; Correspondence.; Performance art -- United States.; Paintings (visual works); Installations (Art) -- United States.; Performance art -- New York (State) -- New York; Scrapbooks.; Juvenilia.; Women artists -- United States.; Feminism and art.; Transcripts.; Press releases.; Astrology.; Religion; Videocassettes.; Chakras.; Costume.; Montano, Linda, 1942-; Wilson, Martha, 1947-; Solomon R. Guggenheim Museum; A.I.R. Gallery (New York, N.Y.); Wilke, Hannah; Payne, Mitchell, 1944-1977; Sprinkle, Annie, 1954-; Hsieh, Tehching, 1950-; Oliveros, Pauline, 1932-2016
- Series I: Art Practice
  Scope and Content
  This series documents Montano's work as a performance artist and writer.
  - Subseries A: Art Administration
    Subseries A includes Montano's administrative papers, which include informal and formal proposals for performances, videos, and text. More informal proposals take the form of handwritten performance ideas, many of which were realized and exist in other parts of her archive. This series also contains her grant applications, loan agreements, business correspondence, and emails with arts organizations, museums, and foundations that range from the beginning of her career to 2014.
    Arrangement
    Subseries A is arranged alphabetically by folder title.
    - Art Life Institute, 1983, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Artist Statement: ISA Problems, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Awards, 1965-1988 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Book List: Amazon, 2008 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Budgets, 1987-1989 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Business Correspondence: A, 1979-2011 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Business Correspondence: B, 1980-2012 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Business Correspondence: C [1 of 2], 1974-2010 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Business Correspondence: C [2 of 2], 1977-2007 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Business Correspondence: D, 1979-2001 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Business Correspondence: E, 1979-1997 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Business Correspondence: F, 1979-2002 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Business Correspondence: G, 1993-2011 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Business Correspondence: H, 1978-2003 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Business Correspondence: I, 1986-2014 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Business Correspondence: J, 1979-1991 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Business Correspondence: K, 1980-2008 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Business Correspondence: L, 1978-2014 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Business Correspondence: M, 1982-2010 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Business Correspondence: N, 1978-2009 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Business Correspondence: O, 1984-2010 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Business Correspondence: P/Q, 1985-2001 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Business Correspondence: R, 1988-2012 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Business Correspondence: S, 1978-2012 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Business Correspondence: T, 1980-2012 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Business Correspondence: U, 1985-1988 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Business Correspondence: V, 1980-2013 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Business Correspondence: W, 1981-2007 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Business Correspondence: X/Y/Z, 1980-1993 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - EMPAC Artist-In-Residence Program Application, 2012 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Grants [1 of 2], 1980-1986 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Grants [2 of 2], 1980-1998 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Handwritten Performance Ideas [1 of 9], undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Handwritten Performance Ideas [2 of 9], undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Handwritten Performance Ideas [3 of 9], undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Handwritten Performance Ideas [4 of 9], undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Handwritten Performance Ideas [5 of 9], undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Handwritten Performance Ideas [6 of 9], undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Handwritten Performance Ideas [7 of 9], undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Handwritten Performance Ideas [8 of 9], undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Handwritten Performance Ideas [9 of 9], undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Lecture: Mask, Gershwin Hotel, undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Letters of Recommendation [1 of 2], 1978-2011 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Letters of Recommendation [2 of 2], 1990-2000 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Linda Montano CV/Resumes, 1970-2013 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Loan Agreements, Permissions, and Contracts [1 of 4], 1976-2009 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Loan Agreements, Permissions, and Contracts [2 of 4], 1986-2014 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Loan Agreements, Permissions, and Contracts [3 of 4], 1981-2003 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Loan Agreements, Permissions, and Contracts [4 of 4], 1979-2002 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Material for Website, January 2001 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Performance: Art Life Counseling Notebook and Cards, undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Performance: Chicken Co. Inc., November 1970 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Performance Art/Danger/Hazing/Female Trauma/Brain Conference, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Performance Artists Mailing List, undated (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Performance documentation, [1985]-2013 (Box 4, Folder 12)
      This folder includes documentation related to the following performances: "Why Laughter Exercises," undated, "Subconscious Re-doing," [2003], "Chicken Co., Inc.," [1985], "The Art/Life Decision Club," undated, "Forgiveness Performance with Jessica Wyman," undated, "Japanese Talk," undated, "Problems Anonymous: Send your Problems to the Internet," 1995, and "Performance in Gdansk," 2013.
    - Performance: Go To Your Room, at University of Texas: Austin, December 8-11, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Performance Emails, 2001, 2002, 2008 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Performance Proposals: Miscellaneous, 1994, 2007, undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Performance Proposals: Teaching Proposals [1 of 2], undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Performance Proposals: Teaching Proposals [2 of 2], undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Plays Performed at Zen Arts Center, 1981-1983 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Proposal: The Snake Dancer, undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Video Texts and Proposals [1 of 5], undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Video Texts and Proposals [2 of 5], undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Video Texts and Proposals [3 of 5], undated (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Video Texts and Proposals [4 of 5], undated (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Video Texts and Proposals [5 of 5], undated (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Subseries B: Writing
    Subseries B follows Montano's work as the author of several published works. These works include Art in Everyday Life, Letters from Linda Montano, and You Too Are a Performance Artist. The subseries also includes drafts and interviews Montano compiled for the book Performance Artists Talking in the '80s, in which artists talk about food, sex, death, and money. There are also book galleys, correspondence, artists' statements, and smaller pieces written for articles and exhibition catalogues.
    This subseries is arranged alphabetically by title of work.
    - 7 Years of Living Art: 7 Chakras, 1984-1998 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - 7 Years of Living Art and Art Life Institute Proposals, 1975-1991 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - 7 Years of Living Art + Another 7 Years of Living Art Bound Draft, 1983-1991, 1991-1998 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - 7 Years of Living Art: Complete Document, 2013 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - "7 Years of Living Art" Essay by Moira Roth, undated (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - 7 Years of Living Art: "Failing to Repeat", 1999, undated (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - 7 Years of Living Art Guides, undated (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - 7 Years of Living Art: Handwritten Notes, undated (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - 7 Years of Living Art Instruction Cards and Chart, 1984 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - 7 Years of Living Art Journal, 1983-1991 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - 7 Years of Living Art: Year Two, Orange, 1985 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - 7 Years of Living Art Manuscript; 14 Years of Living Art Publication, 1991-2016 (Box Shared Fales 108, Folder 2)
    - 14 Years of Living Art Galley for Future Book, 2013 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Another 7 Years of Living Art, undated (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Another 7 Years of Living Art at the United Nations Flyers, 1991-1999 (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Art in Everyday Life Galley: Chapter 1, undated (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Art in Everyday Life Galley: Chapters 2-4, undated (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Art in Everyday Life Galley: Chapters 5-6, undated (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Art in Everyday Life Galley: Chapters 7-8, undated (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Art in Everyday Life Handbook: Bound, undated (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Art in Everyday Life Photographs, undated (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Art in Everyday Life: Proof Copy, undated (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - "Art in Everyday Life...Published by Astro Artz", undated (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Art/Life: Attention, undated (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Art/Life Institute Handbook Galley, undated (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Art/Life Institute History, Cards, Flyers, undated (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Art/Life Institute Rationale, March 1981, undated (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Art/Life Institute Statement of Plans, [1983] (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Art/Life Reality Letters, to Linda Montano, from Linda Montano, 2002 (Box 8, Folder 9A)
    - "7 Spiritual Lives of Linda M. Montano", undated (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - "Art and Life", July 1977 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - "Art and the Cross", May 6, 1980 (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - "Art as Therapy", August-September 1980 (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - "The Art of Attention...The Attention of Art", 1980 (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - "Audience and the Art of Linda Montano", 1999 (Box 8, Folder 15)
    - "Autobiography", undated (Box 8, Folder 16)
    - Beverly Ogdon on Singing, January-May 1981 (Box 8, Folder 16A)
    - "blindfold", undated (Box 8, Folder 17)
    - Blood Family Art / Dad Art, 2001 (Box 8, Folder 18)
    - CAA Talk: Illness and Art, 2007 (Box 8, Folder 19)
    - Chakraphonics, undated (Box 8, Folder 20)
    - Characters from "Learning to Talk", undated (Box 8, Folder 21)
    - "The Chicken Who Learned to Fly", March 1985 (Box 8, Folder 21A)
    - "Chinmayananda", undated (Box 8, Folder 22)
    - The Cleveland Performance Art Festival, April 1999 (Box 8, Folder 23)
    - "Death", 1991 (Box 8, Folder 24)
    - Death Writing, 1988, 1991, undated (Box 8, Folder 25)
    - "Deborah Hay and Her Influence", undated (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - "A Difference Between Male and Female Performance", undated (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - "Distribute Later", undated (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Dr. Mehta and Seven Thoughts, 2004 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - "Does Technology Invite Isolation or Participation?", January 3, 1979 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Early Poems, undated (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - "Eleanor Montano, 1910-", undated (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - "Endurance: Then and Now", undated (Box 9, Folder 7a)
    - The Essential Writings of Linda Montano [1 of 3], February 2004 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - The Essential Writings of Linda Montano [2 of 3], February 2004 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - The Essential Writings of Linda Montano [3 of 3], February 2004 (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - "The Facing Life Award", undated (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - Fairy Tales, undated (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - "feathers", undated (Box 9, Folder 13)
    - "Five Nights of Living Art", undated (Box 9, Folder 14)
    - "Food and Art Lecture", 1980 (Box 9, Folder 15)
    - "Forgiveness as Spring Cleaning", May 2001 (Box 9, Folder 15a)
    - "Good and Evil", July 1977 (Box 9, Folder 16)
    - "Guess My Salary / Win This Crucifix", November 1994 (Box 9, Folder 17)
    - Haikus, 2012 (Box 137, Folder 1)
    - "How to Corrct [sic]", April 1978 (Box 9, Folder 18)
    - Instructions, undated (Box 9, Folder 19)
    - Intro to Talk at Unitarian Congregation, 2010 (Box 9, Folder 20)
    - Journal Excerpt by Linda Montano, undated (Box 9, Folder 21)
    - Keynote Speech: Art in Odd Places, 2011 (Box 9, Folder 22)
    - Letter to Jill at the Village Voice, 1978 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Letter to "J.J.", October 4, 1984 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Letter to Sartoro and Susanna, undated (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - "Letter to Senior Citizen Gym Teacher", [2011] (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Letters from Linda: Bound Book Proposal and Resume, 2001 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Letters from Linda: Bound Draft of Interviews with Linda M. Montano, 2002 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Letters from Linda: Bound Draft of Writings by Linda M. Montano, 2002 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Letters from Linda: Bound Unedited First Draft, 2002 (Box 10, Folder 8)